Speaker: I’d like you to look at the images and think about what jobs you can see.
You’re almost certainly thinking ‘postman’, ‘fireman’, ‘policeman’.
The English language is evolving.
Many words and expressions that were in regular use are now no longer acceptable in modern society.
They reflect the male-dominated social structures of past eras, and,
as a result, they discriminate against women.
The trend nowadays is towards gender-neutrality, that is, to use language which includes everybody.
Here are five ways in which you can make your language gender-neutral.
Firstly, it’s best to use a neutral word if possible.
The suffix -man was used to describe many social roles
and occupations because they were traditionally performed by men.
However, in the 1970s, as women were increasingly taking on more significant social
and professional roles, people started to replace chairman with chairperson or chair.
Now jobs, once mainly done by men, are increasingly carried out by either sex
and the gender-neutral suffix -person is preferred:
so, spokesperson instead of spokesman, salesperson instead of salesman.
However, we don’t always automatically substitute -person for -man.
Sometimes a gender-neutral alternative has evolved.
For example, we say police officer rather than policeman or policewoman.
Other examples include fire fighter rather than fireman,
refuse collector rather than dustman, and flight attendant rather than air hostess.
A second way to make language gender-neutral is to avoid the suffix -ess – that’s E-S-S.
This suffix, which has been used since medieval times,
is added to a male noun to indicate the equivalent role for a woman.
For example, manager–manageress, actor–actress.
By the end of the 20th century,
it was no longer considered relevant to specify whether a job was being done by a man or a woman.
The female form was seen as patronizing to women and fell out of fashion,
and the male form became the standard term.
So now, for example, both men and women are managers or actors.
Thirdly, don’t say man when you mean everybody.
This is a less obvious change that it’s easy to forget about.
In Old English, the word man meant human being,
but now, to refer to humanity in general, try to avoid the use of man or mankind.
There are a number of gender-neutral alternatives, depending on the context.
Talk about the future of the human race, for example, rather than the future of mankind.
Instead of describing a manpower shortage, refer to a shortage of staff or workers.
Don’t ask somebody to man the front desk – it can be staffed or run.
The adjective man-made is easily replaced by synthetic or artificial, whilst the opinion
of the man in the street is really just the opinion of the average person or ordinary people.
Another important thing is to use woman, not girl.
An absolute no-no is to use girl to refer to any woman in a particular job or role.
This term implies that women are in some way immature, children rather than adults.
So, for example, while in the past, a man might have referred to the weather girl on morning TV,
it is much more appropriate now to describe this person as
‘the woman who presents the weather’ or use the gender-neutral term weather presenter.
The final piece of advice is to beware of binomials.
Binomials, phrases consisting of two words joined by a conjunction, such as and,
typically place the male word before the female, so men and women, boys and girls,
brothers and sisters, and Mr and Mrs.
Just remember, you don’t have to put the male word first: mix it up, girls and boys!
Society is changing and the English language is evolving to match.
You are still likely to hear gendered language.
But keep your eyes and ears open, be careful what you say, and go as gender-neutral as you can!